Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太と➡
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
日本人初のムーンウォーカーと
ひびと
なった弟･日々人＞
Younger brother Hibito has become the first Japanese moonwalker.
Mutta seeks to become an astronaut, and keep his promise to former teacher Sharon, to build a telescope on the moon.
＜月面望遠鏡建設を望む恩師
シｬロンとの約束を果たすため➡
六太は宇宙飛行士を目指す＞
Mutta's made it through the first round, but he keeps running into trouble.
かろ
＜選抜試験を辛うじて突破するも
訓練中もトラブルの連続！＞
＜筆記試験では最低点｡暴走教官が
飛行訓練の担当になる始末＞
On the written test, he scores the lowest.
And as a result, he's assigned to a wild flight instructor.
Until he solves how to improve the lunar buggy, he can't begin training for lunar missions.
＜月面バギー開発で
成果を出さなければ➡
月を目指す訓練を
受けることはできない＞
But now, Mutta is finally one step closer to the moon.
＜しかし 六太は今ついに
月面に向けて➡
新たな一歩を
踏み出そうとしていた！＞
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)なぜ ヒビチョフが
帰らなきゃならんのだ！
Why does Hibichov need to return?!
まだリハビリ訓練の途中だぞ！➡
He's still undergoing rehab.
セーフティー
安全スーパーバイザーなど…➡
Safety Supervisor is a position for retired astronauts...
宇宙飛行士を引退してからでも
できる仕事だろ！
なんば
(南波日々人)明日には帰れってさ｡
I'm heading back tomorrow.
もう少し先に延ばしてくれって
頼んだけど…聞く耳ねぇや｡
I requested some more time, but they weren't having it.
辛抱強く 復帰することだけ
考え続けるんだ｡
So you must endure, and focus on returning to active duty.
《イヴァンの言う通り
自分ひとりでも➡
Ivan's right.
I'll have to overcome the panic disorder myself.
パニック障害を
克服するしかない…》
(オリガ)じゃね！イエーイ！
Bye! Yay!
ああ じゃあな オリガ｡
Yeah! Goodbye, Olga!
《パニック障害を治したら…➡
Once I've gotten rid of this panic disorder,
今度は堂々と
またロシアに来る…》
I can return to Russia on my own terms.
I'll come back to see you...
《また会いに来るよ》
《オリガ…》
Olga.
(南波六太)できた！
All done!
(ﾋﾟｰﾀｰ)ああ 余裕だな｡
Yeah, that was easy.
Our first prototype is finished!
(ダン)試作品第一号 完成～！
イエーイ！やった～!!
ワオ！素晴らしい！
Yay! We did it!
Wonderful!
グッジョブ!!
Good job!
(ビンス)ミスターナンバ｡
Mr. Nanba...
なんだ…？
What's this?
どこでもいい
とりあえず席について｡
Find a place to sit.
(ﾊﾞﾄﾗｰ)全員そろったら説明する｡
I'll begin once everyone's here.
これは…どういうメンツなのかね｡
What's this meeting about?
(ケンジ)さあ…｡
I'm not sure.
ここでの仕事は今日までです｡
This will be your last day working here.
ついて来て下さい｡
そろそろ始まります｡
Please come with me. It's time to begin.
Huh?
え…な 何がですか？
What's about to begin?
It's time to begin
これから 君は…
月を目指します｡
your journey to the moon.
い…い～んすか!?目指しても｡
A-Am I really allowed to begin that?
Swayed by a profound sadness
My daydreams lay a bouquet at my feet
space brothers
I stand atop a brand new world
Hoping to catch whatever falls out of this unprecedented miracle
They're here yet again
The days I'll spend growing distant from you
I'll have miles to go before I sleep in peace
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It got mixed into your blood one day and hasn't let you go
That's all
My body grows nimbler by the day
And my heart's shedding tears because it can't keep up
But I lost something once I became an adult
My light slumber
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It's mixed into your blood, so I'll never let you go
That's all
My body stands atop a stage that it won't run away from even if it rains
That makes me break out into a sprint, so goodbye
My midnight slumbers
#80 Secret
I'm...
《月を…➡
月を目指す…!!》
I'm on my way to the moon.
《とうとう…俺も月の訓練を!!》
Finally...
I get to train for the moon!
《うおお～っ!!》
ど～したんだ ムッタ…｡
いがんでる？
What's wrong, Mutta?
Did you strain something?
つったんじゃないの？背中とか｡
He probably threw out his back...
さあ 行きますよ｡
Now, come with me.
あっ ちょっと待って下さい｡
Ah, h-hold on...
あいさつ
最後に みんなに挨拶を｡
Let me say goodbye to the guys first.
(ﾋﾟｰﾀｰ)って事は…➡
Then that means you're quitting, Mutta?
ここを やめちゃうのね ムッタ｡
(ﾊﾛﾙﾄﾞ)急だな｡
Seems sudden.
悪いな みんな｡
でも こうなったのも➡
Sorry, guys...
But you all helped to make this possible.
みんなのおかげだ｡ありがとな！
Thanks.
こちらこそ｡
フロントナビの試作品が➡
We should thank you.
And we just finished the front navigation system prototype.
できたとこだってのに…
残念だよ｡
It's too bad.
みんななら きっと上手くいく｡
I'm sure you guys can make it work!
We've learned a lot from you.
我々も君から多くを学んだよ｡
ありがとう｡
Thank you.
寂しいなぁ～｡ホント寂しいよ｡
でも オメデトウ｡
It's sad... Really very sad.
But I congratulate you.
次は 女の子をよこすように
君から上に頼んどいてね｡
Make sure to ask the bigwigs to send a girl next...
ハァ…｡
よし！じゃあ
行ってくるよ みんな！
Okay!
Then, I'm off, guys!
ああ 頑張れ！
Yeah, good luck!
行くって どこ行くの？
Where exactly are you going?
月へな！
To the moon!
フフン｡
早くして下さい｡
Please hurry up.
Ah, s-sorry for that.
あっ すみません｡行きましょう｡
Let's go.
忘れてたけど そ～いや あいつ
宇宙飛行士だったな｡
I completely forgot that he was an astronaut.
忘れてたね｡
So did I.
今から説明会があります｡➡
The orientation is about to start.
私やラリー そして君も含め➡
Twelve astronauts, including you, Larry, and me, will participate in this training.
１２名の飛行士が
この訓練に参加します｡
ど…どんな訓練なんすか？
Wh-What kind of training?
｢地球上で一番
月面を再現できる場所｣➡
If I tell you that this training will take place
in the environment most similar to that of the moon, you should be able to deduce the rest.
そこで行われる訓練と言えば
君にも分かるでしょう｡
マ…マジすか!?
S-Seriously?!
《てことは…➡
That means...
すげえ～!!》
Awesome!
《やったぜ 日々人！
お前は今頃 寒～いロシアで➡
I did it, Hibito...
Meanwhile, you're freezing away in Russia, training in the Soyuz or something.
ソユーズ訓練か何かを
しているのだろう｡フッフッフッ》
《俺は これから
ニーモ
｢ＮＥＥＭＯ｣訓練だ！》
I'm about to begin NEEMO training!
Mu!
(ケンジ)ムッ君！
Hey, it's Kenji!
にった
おお ケンジ！うわっ 新田もか！
And Nitta, too?
んんっ 早く座りなさい｡
待ってたんだ｡
Please be seated... We've been waiting for you.
Ah, yes, Chief Butler...
あ はいっ バトラー室長｡
ああっ…！別に…!!
彼とは何もないからな!!
There's nothing between him and me!
Hmm? What do you mean?
Now, then...
さて 君達 宇宙飛行士１２名の
新たな訓練を説明しよう｡
I will explain the new training that the twelve astronauts in this room will undergo.
３日後から２週間
ＮＥＥＭＯを実践してもらう｡➡
Beginning tomorrow, you will be participating in two weeks of NEEMO.
You will live at the bottom of the ocean, in a simulated lunar environment,
海の底…
水深２０メートルに設置された➡
twenty meters below sea level.
仮想月面基地での
シミュレーション生活だ｡➡
死の危険も伴う
油断できない訓練だ｡➡
This training requires vigilance, as your lives will be in real danger.
Prepare yourselves before going in.
心して取り組むように｡
Before they can participate in NEEMO,
＜ＮＥＥＭＯ訓練を
するにあたって➡
astronauts must demonstrate a certain level of swimming ability.
宇宙飛行士には泳ぐ力が
ある程度 求められる＞
There are three tests.
＜テスト項目は３つ＞
＜１つ目は４００メートルを
１２分以内で泳ぐこと＞
The first test involves swimming four hundred meters within twelve minutes.
＜１２分以内でゴールすれば
泳ぎ方は何でもＯＫ＞
As long as you beat the time limit, you may use any stroke.
《この人は
水泳選手か何かだろうか？》
Was this guy a competitive swimmer?
うわっ！ぶるるる…｡
Damn!
《チキショー！カｯコつけやがって
新田のヤロウ!!》
Nitta's showing off!
《でも いいな～ バタフライ》
But I wish I could do the butterfly.
If I tried, I'd look like I was drowning.
《俺があれやると 溺れてるように
しか見えないんだよな～》
《いいな～》
Lucky guy...
＜テスト項目２つ目は
立ち泳ぎ１０分間＞
The second test is treading water for ten minutes.
＜立ち泳ぎといっても とにかく
浮かんでればＯＫというルｰル＞
However, the rules only require you to stay afloat,
＜だから これでＯＫなのだ＞
so you can just do this.
Crap, my right leg's cramping up.
《あ ヤバい…
右足がつりそうだ くぅ～！》
Hang in there, right leg!
《もってくれよ 俺の右足!!》
＜そして
３つ目のテスト項目が…➡
And the third test
２５メートルの潜水だ＞
is swimming twenty-five meters underwater.
ぷはぁっ…！
《危ねぇ～！
一瞬 意識が飛んだ…》
Damn... I almost blacked out!
ダァ～ッ！ハァハァハァ…｡
もうやめろって…ムグッ…｡
クゥン クン…｡
Cut it out!
プハッ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
ハァ～｡
《あ～あ…
ＮＥＥＭＯまで あと２日か…》
Two days until NEEMO starts...
《楽しみすぎるぜ！》
I can't wait.
Huh?
オミヤゲ｡
Here's your souvenir.
おい 日々人！…あれ!?
Hibito! What?
フフッ…ただいま｡
I'm back.
お前…ロシア
もう 終わったの？
You already finished what you were doing in Russia?
[ﾗｼﾞｵ](ﾗｼﾞｵ:ＤＪ)
聴くと元気になる
モーニングレディオ➡
It's Morning Radio, the show that wakes you up!
Ｑ＆Ａのコーナー｡
イエ～！
Time for the Q&A corner. Yeah!
[ﾗｼﾞｵ](ﾗｼﾞｵ:ＤＪ)
ロスにお住まいのカール君
８歳からの質問｡➡
We have a question from eight-year-old Carl, out in LA.
"It seems crazy that Santa Claus can deliver everyone's presents in one night.
｢サンタさんは
たった一晩で みんなに➡
プレゼントを配るなんて
スゴすぎると思うんですけど➡
なんでそんなスゴいことが
できるんですか？｣｡
How does he pull it off?"
[ﾗｼﾞｵ](ﾗｼﾞｵ:ＤＪ)なるほど｡➡
Ah, that's an excellent question, Carl.
いい質問だね カール君｡
よし 教えてあげよう…➡
I'll give you the answer...
ホントにスゴいのは…➡
The credit all goes
｢トナカイ｣だよ～！
to the reindeer!
《思い出すなぁ
サンタのバイト…》
That just reminded me...
of my stint as Santa.
で…どうだったよ ロシアは？
So how was Russia?
ああ…寒かったよ｡
Oh, it was cold.
気温 聞いてんじゃね～よ！
訓練だ 訓練｡
I wasn't asking about the weather...
How did your training go?
あと 美人に出会ったかどうか｡
And did you meet any pretty ladies?
まあ…
美人なら１人いたけど…➡
Well...
There was this one pretty girl,
彼女は あれだ｡
年が俺とは倍の差がある｡
but we're talking a difference of twice the age.
Twice?!
｢倍｣って…お前
えっ ６０!?
Wait...
She's sixty?
You have it backwards! She's fifteen!
逆だよ １５！
１５…なんだよ
子供じゃね～か｡
Fifteen?
Oh, then she's just a kid...
まあね｡ムッちゃんは
ＮＥＥＭＯが始まるんだっけ？
Well, yeah.
I hear you're about to start NEEMO?
そのと～り｡月へ行くための➡
That's right!
I've reached the first stage of a lunar mission.
第一段階に来たわけだよ｡
ようやく 俺も｡
It's finally my turn.
《ふ～っ 泣ける…》
I'm tearing up.
そんで お前の次のミッションは
ど～なってんだ？
Do you know what your next mission will be?
Heading back to the moon?
次も月だろ？
Yeah, of course.
ああ そりゃそうだよ｡➡
もうすぐ そっちの訓練に
切り替わるはずだ｡
I start training for it shortly.
お前…何か隠してるだろ｡
Hibito...
There's something you aren't telling me.
その１５歳の娘って➡
Was that fifteen-year-old girl actually a sexy, twenty-something lady?
本当は２０代のセクシー美女
だったんじゃないのか？
ちげ～よ｡
No...
ふうか
(風佳)うわ…あ～…ああ～！
(ケンジ)ホラ こいでこいで｡
(風佳)あ～…あ！
Come on, keep pedaling...
(ケンジ)手ぇ放すよ！
I'm letting go.
There!
(ケンジ)それっ！
(ケンジ)また 右に傾いてるよ！➡
You're leaning right.
No, not like that!
(ケンジ)あっ｡ああ～…｡
ホラ 自転車 起こして｡風佳｡
Pick up your bicycle, Fuuka.
I'm sick of this...
(風佳)もうヤダ なわとびする｡
I wanna jump rope.
Huh? What are you talking about?
(ケンジ)え…何言ってんの｡
まだまだ これからだよ｡
We just started.
I can't do it...
だって できない～｡
If you keep saying that, you'll never learn to ride a bike!
そんなこと言ってたら
いつまでも できないよ！➡
ホラ 早く｡自転車！
Now get back on it.
ふ…ふっ…➡
ふわぁ～～ ああ～！
(風佳)あぁ～ん…｡
(ケンジ)泣いたって知らないよ｡➡
Crying won't help...
自転車に乗れるように
なりたいんだろ｡
Don't you want to learn how to ride a bike?
うっ…う～ ぐすっ｡
(ケンジ)さあ もっかい行こう！➡
Okay, give it another try.
Right!
よ～し！
(ケンジ)それ！
There!
Looking good!
(ケンジ)行くぞ！
(風佳)ああ～あ～！
(ケンジ)ちょっとだけ進んだかな
今日は｡➡
She made a little progress today...
幼稚園の他の子たちは➡
All the other kids at her preschool can ride bikes without training wheels.
ほぼ みんな乗れるんだって｡
補助輪なしで｡
風佳だけ
ちょっと遅れ気味なんだ｡
Fuuka's a little behind the rest.
まあ 僕が時間を取れないのが
一番の原因だろうけど｡
Well, the biggest problem is that I don't have time to teach her.
なるほど…でもまあ
すぐ乗れるようになるよ｡
I see.
Still, she'll get the hang of it soon enough.
それにしても
大きくなったな～｡
Anyway, she's gotten a lot bigger.
She's already five.
もう５歳だからね｡
早え～なぁ｡
Time really flies...
ムック 見て～｡
Look, Mukku!
どれ…うっ｡
近いよ～ フーちゃん｡
What?
It's too close, Fu...
これね ムック描いたんだ｡
I drew you.
うわぁ～
スゴイね～ 上手だ！
Wow! You're a great artist!
(風佳)ちゃんとモジャモジャだよ｡
I made you shaggy.
えっ これ もらってもいいの？
Wait, can I keep this?
うん いいよ｡いらないから！
Sure, I don't need it.
あ…やった～！
Great!
さあ そろそろ時間だね ムッ君｡
Well, it's time, Mu.
(ケンジ)行こうか｡
おう｡
Let's go.
Yeah.
(ユキ)行ってらっしゃい
気をつけてね｡
Have a safe trip.
Take care of yourself.
ああ 行ってくるよ｡何かあったら
こまち
小町さんに連絡してね｡
Yeah, I'm off, then.
If anything comes up, call Komachi.
うん わかってる｡
Yes, I know.
(ユキ)ウフフッ…｡
行ってきま～す｡
I'm off.
ダメ～～！エェ～ン！
No!
(風佳)行かないで～！
(ユキ)あ～あ…｡
Don't go!
大丈夫だよ 風佳｡
２週間くらいで帰ってくるから｡➡
Don't worry, Fuuka...
I'll be back in three weeks.
We'll continue your bicycle lessons then.
そしたら また
自転車の練習しような｡
うわぁ～～ ああ～！
久しぶりに｢かぺ～｣が
聞けるかと思ってたけど…➡
I was thinking I might get to hear another "roo-ra,"
さすがに もう言わないか｡
but I guess she's grown out of it.
もうフツーに
｢がんばれ｣って言えるしね｡
She knows how to say "good luck" now.
なんか ちょっと さみし～なぁ｡
It's a little sad.
確かに…｢かぺ｣が聞けないのは
さみしいけど それよりさ➡
True.
I miss hearing her say "roo-ra,"
but she's learned lots of words, and she can talk to us.
前より ずっと言葉を覚えて
話が通じるようになってきたんだ｡
｢話し合える｣って事の方が
実は もっとうれしい｡
The ability to communicate is much better.
あ でも フーちゃんの妹が
いつか言うかもね｡｢かぺ｣｡
But Fu's little sister could bring the roo-ra back.
確かに！ははっ｡➡
You might be right.
そん時までの お楽しみだね｡
One more thing to look forward to.
Congratulations.
⦅おめでとう｡今日から
君の席だ｡自由にしていい⦆
This will be your office.
It's all yours...
《別に いらね～よ
こんなデカい机…》
I don't need such a big desk.
《じっとしてたって
しょ～がね～｡何かしないと…》
I won't get anywhere, just sitting around.
I have to do something.
《ロシアでの続きをやらないとな｡
あの一見バカげた訓練を…》
I need to continue that ridiculous-looking training I started in Russia.
But how can I do it alone?
《でも ひとりで どうやって…》
はい｡
Yes?
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)やあ ヒビト！
おっ ローリー｡
Hey, Hibito!
L-Lowry...
なんか 君宛てに
ものすごい荷物が届いたよ｡
There's a huge package for you.
Huh?
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)ロシアからだよ｡
It's from Russia.
何だろうね これ…｡
What is all this stuff?
⦅う～ん…｡ん？➡
こいつは もうクリア⦆
He already cleared this one.
⦅ん？⦆
てごわ
⦅こいつは結構 手強いぞ｡
視界も狭いし➡
This costume could prove difficult...
It will reduce his vision.
クンクン…汗臭い！⦆
And it smells like sweat!
なあ ローリー…｡
Hey, Lowry...
Hmm?
秘密…守れるか？
Can you keep a secret?
The hasty hare and the slow and steady turtle
Are both headed toward the place they call their goals
We forgot something very important once we grew up
Forget tomorrow, what can I do right now?
But the two of us
Have always remembered
The importance of taking off
The heavy shackles of hesitation
A brand new world
Is always waiting one step ahead of us
Even our failures will give us strength
And that will be the start of a new world
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#81 Worst Enemy
The story moves to the ocean floor...
＜舞台は海底へ｡
仮想月面基地での訓練が始まる＞
I begin training in a lunar environment simulator.
Having Kenji on my team is reassuring.
＜ウチの班には ケンジがいるから
心強い＞
We have not told the astronauts the purpose of this training.
＜彼らには知らせていない
この訓練の目的があります＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Worst Enemy"